{
  "author": {
    "name": "Thakhani Ramaru".
    "student_nr": 24608491,
    "email": "24608491@sun.ac.za"
  },
  "assignment": [
    {
      "section": "Big Data Value",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Loosely define the term 'data product' and provide an example?",
          "answer": "A data product is an application that uses a combination of data and algorithms to bring value to a business. An example of a data product would be goggle search and Amazon’s recommendation system. ",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "Provide a layman's explanation for what differentiates big data analytics from conventional data analytics?",
          "answer": "What differentiates big data analytics from data analytics is that big data analytics involves processing, analysing and uncovering insights from data that is continuously becoming too large and complex to be analysed/processed using current traditional systems.",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "There are numerous articles online discussing how IoT is driving data volumes and is inextricably linked to big data. Name an IoT device that you come into contact with and what data it may be sending and receiving?",
          "answer": "Cellphone. It sends data about my age, location and websites I frequently visit among other things. It receives targeted advertisements on social media platforms I use based on the information that was sent",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Computing",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "What is on-premise computing?",
          "answer": "On-premise computing involves keeping and using organisation’s data within hardware and its associated software within the location of the organisation",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "How has on-demand cloud computing enabled big data analytics?",
          "answer": "On-demand cloud computing allows the provision of data storage infrastructure that is readily available and quickly scalable and can manage large spikes in data traffic and usage.",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What is a _multi-tenancy_, as it relates to cloud computing?",
          "answer": "Multi tenancy is when various customers with their own type of data are able to share a single cloud computing vendor",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "How could organisations with existing infrastructure leverage _on-demand_ cloud computing?",
          "answer": "Organisations can leverage on the fact that cloud computing allows access to data from any location which can be beneficial as it allows flexibility to support remote work for employees",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "Give an example of a cloud managed service and how its management may be  beneficial (in at least two specific ways, e.g. critical software updates occur automatically with no down time)?",
          "answer": "File hosting services. One benefit is that the files can be accessed from any device at any location given that the device has internet connection",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "What is horizontal vs vertical scaling?",
          "answer": "Vertical scaling is adding more power (CPU, memory, etc.) to your existing servers while horizontal scaling is getting additional servers.",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "What is a significant source of latency in a distributed system?",
          "answer": "The distance between the customer and the cloud computing vendor’s data centres",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "Describe PaaS, Saas, Iaas and provide an example of each?",
          "answer": "Paas gives developers services that allow them to develop and test applications over the internet without worrying about resources such as storage and backup. Apache Strato. Saas allows products to be hosted in the internet by a vendor and delivered by a subscription pricing structure. Microsoft Office 365.Iaas enables organisations to use virtualised resources on the internet for offerings such as server space, data storage, hardware, and networking all coming from a remote data centres. Amazon Web Service.",
          "total_marks": 4
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Programming",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "What is the shared characteristic of R and Python that allows them to make use of a REPL (read-eval-print loop)?",
          "answer": "1.	The shared characteristic between both programming languages is that they are have command-line shells",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose you want to process a large amount of data. In this context, what does it mean if a process is 'I/O bound', and how would you solve/ameliorate this using hardware, or using a language such as python or javascript (or any other language you are more familiar with)?",
          "answer": "2.	The process is “I/O bound” if the rate of reading/writing data is slower than the rate of computation performed on the data by the CPU. From a hardware perspective the problem can be solved by increasing disk volumes in your storage devices in order to improve latency",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "What does serialization mean in the context of storing objects or data?",
          "answer": "3.	Serialisation is the process of converting data structures into a format that can stored, transferred and used in other systems with ease ",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What does it mean when we say that JSON is serializable?",
          "answer": "It means that objects can be converted into JSON format/file",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "Define 'embarrassingly parallelisable' and provide an example in the related to data analytics?",
          "answer": "Embarrassingly parallelisable is used to describe a process or problem where little or no effort is needed to break down problem into a number of parallel tasks. An example graphics processing units for 3D projection where each pixel should be rendered independently",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What paradigm shift allows the Spark's computing engine to be faster than MapReduce?",
          "answer": "Spark does the data processing using RAM while MapReduce has to read from and write to the storage disk ",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "How is java code able to run on multiple operating systems?",
          "answer": "Java can compile into bytecode which can run on any operating system give that the operating system has a virtual machine.",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the difference between a virtual machine (e.g. virtualbox) and containers (e.g. docker)? Which one is more light-weight and which is more secure? ",
          "answer": "A virtual machine emulates a computer system making it possible to run what may appear as many computers on hardware that is one computer while Dockers/containers just virtualise the operating system instead of the underlying computer like in virtual machines. Virtual machines are more secure while containers are more light-weight. ",
          "total_marks": 3
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Streams",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The instruction (using Unix pipes) `tail -f /var/log/syslog | grep CRITICAL` streams system logs into a search command. This is an example of partial-order computation -- a concurrency model. Is it embarrassingly parallelisable? Motivate your answer.",
          "answer": "No, because the instruction has a pipe operator ",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "Although unlikely, suppose that the syslog file grew faster than our ability to search it. What functionality would need to be embedded in the 'pipe' (`|`) operator for us to handle that?",
          "answer": "Add parallel command before the pipe operator ",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What is meant by unbounded data, and how does it differ from bounded data?",
          "answer": "Unbounded data is data that is ever growing and infinite data. It differs from bounded data in the bounded data is finite.",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "Stream processing is an inherently time-related activity; describe the difference between 'event time' and 'processing time' within these systems, and provide a brief example in the banking or retail sector?",
          "answer": "Event time is the time at which the data occurred while processing time is the time at which the data was observed. In the banking sector event time would be using a bank card to withdraw money from the ATM and processing time would receiving an SMS informing you of the transaction you have make at the ATM",
          "total_marks": 3
        },
        {
          "question": "It is possible to process _unbounded_ data in a batch system. If our use-case  does not require near real-time processing, then how would this be done?",
          "answer": "No. This could be done by simply giving time intervals within which the unbounded data came in and using only the data that came in within that interval",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Data Storage",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tape drives are still in wide use around the world. Provide three reasons for their continued use?",
          "answer": "They are energy efficient since they don’t require any energy once data is stored in them and they are stored away. They are highly reliable since their error rates are four to five fold lower than those of hard drives. They are also very secure because of the nature of the medium itself ",
          "total_marks": 3
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the difference between a _kibibyte_ and a _kilobyte_, and which is accurate in terms of storage?",
          "answer": "A kibibyte is 2 to the power 10 which 1024 bytes while a kilobyte is 1000 bytes.  A kilobyte is more accurate for storage",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "If a compact disk is 1.2mm thick, and can store 700MiB on a single disk, then how many pebibytes (PiB) of data would be stored on a hypothetical column of compact disks stacked between the Earth and the Moon? How many exbibytes (EiB)?",
          "answer": "Distance from the earth to the moon is 384 400 km which is equal to 384 400*1000000 mm. The n umber of compact discs from earth to the moon is 384 400*1000000/1.2=320 333 333 333.333 discs. Thus the total size is (700*320 333 333 333.33)/ (1024*1024*1024) =208 833.5653 PiB. Which is also equal to 203.939 EiB. ",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly described what is meant when people refer to SQL and NoSQL databases and provide an example of a type of data typically stored in NoSQL databases?",
          "answer": "SQL databases are databases that use structured query language for defining and manipulating data that has a relational model. An example of SQL data type would be numeric latitude and longitude of locations.  NoSQL databases have dynamic schemas for unstructured data. And the data is stored in many different forms. An example of NoSQL data would be a combination of graphs and tables ",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "_Wide-column_ and _key-value_ stores are examples of NoSQL database types. Can you name two more?",
          "answer": "Document store and graphs.",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": " What makes Avro self-describing, and does Google's ProtoBuf also have this feature? Why is this a useful?",
          "answer": "It specifies the data type of whatever it is describing inside the format. Google’s protobuf does not have this feature. This ensures that a reader can handle serialized data.",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "When comparing random access memory (RAM) to conventional solid state disks and rota disks (normal rotational), how many orders of magnitude faster is _main memory_ or RAM (these are approximate calculations that may ignore the differences between read and write operations)?",
          "answer": "RAM is 20 to 30 times faster than typical solid state disks",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Processes, People and Principles",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Big data teams often include, amongst other roles, data engineers and data scientists. Provide a few differentiating responsibilities between these two roles?",
          "answer": "Data engineers have advanced programming skills  and good skills in data warehousing while data scientists have advanced statistical skills and good skills in data mining ",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "Why is data lineage important in analytics applications?",
          "answer": "Data lineage is important because being able to trace data to its source can help in understadning the requirements of a new software development process",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "The operation of reading data from a database may be said to be _idempotent_. Suppose  we fill our online shopping cart with items, and proceed to checkout. Would we want the  checkout process to be idempotent, and why? ",
          "answer": "Yes. It allows the development of fault tolorent application interface programming"
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "What is CICD?",
          "answer": "CICD (Continuous integration and continuous delivery) allows the delivery of software to it’s users with speed, safety, and reliability",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What is DataOps?",
          "answer": "A practice used by data analytics teams in order to improve the quality of the data analysis process",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "When is data _immutable_ and why is it it a useful concept in the big data realm (e.g. consider Hadoop's HDFS filesystem or S3 buckets in AWS)?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Tooling",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "What is a metastore/metadata server in distributed systems and why is it important (e.g. consider the Hive Metastore in the Hadoop environment, NameNodes in the Hadoop Filesystem, or Metadata Servers in Ceph)?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "What kind of database is Cassandra and what kind of workloads is it suited for (i.t.o read/writes)?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 2
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the H2O platform and what underlying design/operational choice does it share with Spark?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "If I create a feature branch `feature/biglie` off `master` in git, and someone makes a code change to master, how do I get their changes into my branch?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Analytics",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "How do we know if a machine learning model will perform well 'in the wild'?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        },
        {
          "question": "Suppose you are building a model on a large dataset (>500GiB) and have limited time for discovery work and limited budget. How do you approach feature engineering and model estimation in a reasonable way?",
          "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 1
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "section": "Submission",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Generate an openssh/RSA public-private key pair. Submit the public key on the SUNLearn platform. A server address will be provided in due course. You may then transfer/deliver the completed assignment (e.g. `12345678-preblock.json`) using the `ssh` or `sftp` protocol",
         "answer": "",
          "total_marks": 3
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
